<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The schole of godly feare a sermon preached at the assises holden in Exeter, March 20, 1614.</title>
            <author>Bury, John, 1580-1667.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17334</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4180.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S262</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22162224</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22162224</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25202</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17334)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25202)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1747:33)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The schole of godly feare a sermon preached at the assises holden in Exeter, March 20, 1614.</title>
                  <author>Bury, John, 1580-1667.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Stansby for Henry Fetherstone,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Iohn Bery.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴.</note>
                  <note>Title within ornamental border.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Peter, 1st, I, 17 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Fear of God --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="engraved_title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25202:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25202:1"/>
            <p>THE SCHOLE OF GODLY FEARE. A Sermon preached <hi>at the Aſsiſes holden in</hi> Exeter, March 20. 1614.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 111.10.</hi>
               </bibl> The feare of the Lord is the beginning of wiſedome; a good vnderſtanding haue all they that doe thereafter.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 34.11.</hi>
               </bibl> Come, ye children, harken vnto me; I will teach you the feare of the Lord.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MAL. 1.6.</hi>
               </bibl> If I be a Father, where is mine honour? If I be a Lord, where is my feare?</q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>William Stansby</hi> for <hi>Henry Fetherſtone.</hi> 1615.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:25202:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25202:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE SIR HENRY HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BART Knight, LORD Chiefe Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the Common Pleas, and Sir LAV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RENCE TANFIELD <hi>Knight, Lord chiefe</hi> Baron of his Maieſties Exchequer, continuance <hi>and multiplication of all heauenly Graces</hi> and earthly bleſſings.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Sermon, being at firſt exacted by <hi>reuerend</hi> authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſince pulled foorth by violent importunity, and euen preſſed to the Preſſe, inioyeth this onely freedome, that it runneth cheerefully to your Lordſhips
<pb facs="tcp:25202:3"/>hands, preſenting it ſelfe a true (howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ſlender) teſtimony of the Authors thankefull and dutifull reſpect, of your honourable fauours, not onely in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar towards himſelfe, whom you haue beene pleaſed to grace farre beyond de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert; but alſo in generall to Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, whom with a iuſt and zealous care, you as <hi>Gods vpon earth</hi> protect from oppreſsion. Who ſeeth not, how reſolute witneſſes hauing armed themſelues to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a tractable Iury, with as formall a tale, as the <hi>two Elders</hi> had deuiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Suſanna;</hi> your Lordſhip full of the ſpirit of <hi>Daniel,</hi> that is, <hi>the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God</hi> (for ſo his name ſignifieth) by prudent ſifting, and vnexpected inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatories, haue bunted out, and diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued their plotted falſhood? Who ſeeth not, how vnaccuſtomed cuſtomes incro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
<pb facs="tcp:25202:3"/>vpon the <hi>Lords</hi> portion, allotted and allowed to his <hi>Laborers,</hi> haue ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as faire pretences of remote Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as were the <hi>old ſackes, old bottles, old clothes, and mouled bread</hi> of the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> when your diſcreet inquiry before the Inqueſt hath eſpied and deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their neere bordering neighbourhood? In a word, your Chriſtian care to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the <hi>hedge</hi> of Iuſtice for a fence to the <hi>Lords vine</hi> (that <hi>euery one which paſſeth by,</hi> may not <hi>plucke of her grapes)</hi> putteth into our mouthes a ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full gratulation, that your Honours are none of them that ſeek honor, by <hi>muzze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the mouth of the Oxe, that trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth out the Corne.</hi> And this leadeth vs to a farther duty, <hi>viz.</hi> to looke vp to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Heauen vnto him, that <hi>looketh downe from heauen</hi> vpon vs, to <hi>behold
<pb facs="tcp:25202:4"/>and viſit his vine, which he hath plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with his owne right hand, and made ſtrong for himſelfe:</hi> and as hee hath giuen vs ſuch <hi>nurſing Fathers,</hi> ſo we to returne vnto him prayſe for your good beginnings, and prayer for your good continuance, to the glorie of his Name, the vpholding of his Church, the incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of his Miniſters, and your owne eternall reward, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in all duty, IOHN BERY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:25202:4"/>
            <head>THE SCHOLE OF GODLY FEARE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1. PET. 1.17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And if yee call him Father, who without reſpect of perſons, iudgeth according to euery mans worke, paſſe the time of your dwelling here in feare.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His verſe conſiſteth of a <hi>Doctrine</hi> and his <hi>Vſe.</hi> The Doctrine teacheth vs how to looke vpon <hi>God, Ye call him Father, &amp;c.</hi> The Vſe warneth vs how to looke to our <hi>ſelues: Paſſe the time of your dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling here in feare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Doctrine propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth <hi>God</hi> to our view (like <hi>Ianus Bifrons)</hi> as hauing two faces.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, the chearefull countenance of a <hi>Father, Ye call him Father.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:25202:5"/>
               <item>Secondly, the ſeuere countenance of a <hi>Iudge, who with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect of perſons, iudgeth according to euery mans worke.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>If ye call him Father]</hi> We neede not curiouſly diſcuſſe the ſeeming difference of Tranſlations.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> The <hi>Greeke</hi> phraſe here vſed, being compared with other like places of Scripture (as <hi>Iames</hi> 2.7. <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 48.5.16. <hi>Eſay</hi> 4.1.) yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vnto vs this plaine ſenſe: <hi>If yee call him Father,</hi> that is, if yee will paſſe for his children, and profeſſe him to be your Father: which we may done three wayes.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. By pretending to the eies of others in <hi>ſhew.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. By preſuming in our owne hearts by <hi>perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. By conteſting vnto his owne face in <hi>prayer;</hi> that he is our Father, and we his children.</item>
            </list>
            <p>But <hi>quo iure?</hi>
               <note place="margin">God is our Father.</note> by what claime? <hi>Father</hi> is a royall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue, originally and <hi>primarily</hi> due vnto <hi>God</hi> alone, <hi>(Matth.</hi> 23.9. <hi>Call no man father vpon the earth, for one is your Father which is in heauen)</hi> but due to others <hi>ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darily,</hi> and vnder him: and to him it is due both by <hi>Creation</hi> and <hi>Generation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Creation inueſted him with an <hi>Vniuerſall</hi> Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood ouer all creatures:
<note place="margin">1. By Creation</note> but among all, <hi>principally</hi> of <hi>Adam,</hi> who alone reſembled his <hi>Father,</hi> being made to the <hi>Image</hi> of his Maker <hi>(Geneſ.</hi> 1.27.) and ſtiled, <hi>Adam the ſonne of God, Luke</hi> 3.38.</p>
            <p>Nor is he Father of <hi>Adam</hi> alone, but of <hi>vs</hi> alſo, and of both parts of vs, our <hi>bodies</hi> and our <hi>ſoules:</hi> of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies <hi>mediately</hi> and <hi>virtually</hi> created in <hi>Adams</hi> loines; and of our ſoules <hi>actually</hi> and <hi>immediately</hi> infuſed by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. For our bodies indeed, we are bound to thank <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres carnis,</hi> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord hath ſubſtituted to be our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:25202:5"/>according to the fleſh: but for our ſoules, our ſoules muſt be lifted vp vnto <hi>Patrem ſpirituu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (Heb.</hi> 12.9.) the Father of ſpirits, <hi>qui infundendo creat, &amp; creando in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundit,</hi> who at one, and the ſame inſtant, both createth and infuſeth them into theſe earthly manſions of their fleſhly tabernacle.</p>
            <p>But what comfort is it, thus to ſalute him by the name of <hi>father,</hi> in this peculiar language before other creatures, ſeeing the vnhappieſt of all his creatures, the damned <hi>reprobates,</hi> that ſhall neuer come neere him, or his patrimony, are yet as neere as we to this <hi>paternitie?</hi> and may take vp the Prophets words, <hi>Malach.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Haue we not all one Father? hath not one God made vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore ſeeing this is too low,
<note place="margin">2. By Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</note> mount we higher from Creation to <hi>Generation:</hi> and here wee finde one Sonne begotten of his <hi>Nature,</hi> and others begotten of his <hi>Grace.</hi> I ſay, <hi>one</hi> of his nature, that is, <hi>one</hi> with him in nature, a Sonne as <hi>old,</hi> and as <hi>good</hi> as his Father, <hi>coeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall,</hi> and <hi>coequall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as the former was too low,
<note place="margin">Not of nature,</note> ſo this is too high a ſtraine, vnto which, neither men, nor yet <hi>Angels</hi> can reach: for <hi>vnto which of the Angels ſaid hee at any time, Thou art my Sonne, this day haue I begotten thee? Heb.</hi> 1.5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In medio virtus noſtra:</hi>
               <note place="margin">But of Grace.</note> the ſinewes of our comfort lye in the middeſt, <hi>viz.</hi> in the ſonneſhip of <hi>grace:</hi> by which a <hi>remnant</hi> of mankind, <hi>through the election of grace (Rom.</hi> 11.5.) are ſeparated in the name, and for the ſake of the <hi>naturall</hi> beloued Sonne, to be <hi>ſonnes,</hi> and <hi>heires,</hi> and <hi>coheires</hi> with him of euerlaſting glory, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17. for which purpoſe, he granted forth a <hi>Dedimus poteſtate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> and <hi>as many as receiued him (poteſtatem dedit) to them hee
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:25202:6"/>gaue power to be the ſonnes of God, euen to them that beleeue on his name, Ioh.</hi> 1.12.</p>
            <p>For this inheritance,
<note place="margin">The couenant of grace.</note> a <hi>Couenant of grace</hi> is drawne vp betweene vs, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.18. conſiſting of two parts: 1. what is performed on <hi>Gods</hi> behalfe, by his free <hi>Adoption; I will be a Father vnto you.</hi> 2. What is to be performed on our parts by our bounden <hi>Renouation: Ye ſhall be my ſons and daughters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Vpon this couenant a paire of <hi>Indentures</hi> are engroſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
<note place="margin">Aſſured by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denture.</note> and interchangeably ſealed by both parties. The former part (containing our Sonneſhip by <hi>adoption)</hi> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in record in <hi>Gods</hi> eternall <hi>preſcience,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The originall.</note> hauing two <hi>ſeales</hi> appendent, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. <hi>viz.</hi> on the behalfe <hi>of</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>God,</hi> his Seale of euerlaſting <hi>Decree: the Lord know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth who are his.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Vs,</hi> our Seale of <hi>aſſent,</hi> that <hi>euery one, which calleth (him Father) vpon the name of the Lord, depart from iniquitie.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>counterpane</hi> (containing our Sonneſhip by <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation)</hi> is a <hi>patent</hi> deliuered from God to euery ſon <hi>whom hee recieiueth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pane.</note> which likewiſe hath two Seales affixed: <hi>viz.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. His Seale of the <hi>Spirit.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. Our Seale of <hi>Faith.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>God ſetteth to it the Seale of his Spirit; for <hi>(Eph.</hi> 1.13) <hi>We are ſealed with the holy ſpirit of promiſe, which is the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of our inheritance.</hi> The print of which Seale is the <hi>New man (Coloſſ.</hi> 3.10) <hi>which is renewed in knowledge after the Image of him that created him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Seale of <hi>Faith,</hi> although it be made by Gods owne workmanſhip <hi>(this is the worke of God, that yee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in him, whom he hath ſent, Iohn</hi> 6.29.) and giuen by
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:25202:6"/>his bountie <hi>(not of our ſelues, it is the gift of God, Epheſ.</hi> 2.8.) although, I ſay, in theſe reſpects it is <hi>Gods,</hi> yet it is <hi>our</hi> Scale in <hi>application;</hi> for <hi>he that beleeueth, ſetteth to his ſeale, that God is true, Iohn</hi> 3.33.</p>
            <p>The <hi>patent</hi> thus ſealed,
<note place="margin">The Patents force.</note> hath a double force and vertue:
<list>
                  <item>1. It maketh a man to bee the ſonne and heire of the liuing God.</item>
                  <item>2. It aſſureth a man to bee the ſonne and heire of the liuing God.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>It <hi>maketh</hi> him ſo to be, by inſtalling him in <hi>regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> for <hi>as many as are led by the Spirit of God, they are the ſonnes of God, Rom.</hi> 8.14. and it <hi>aſſureth</hi> him ſo to be, by giuing euidence of his <hi>adoption, verſ.</hi> 16. <hi>the ſame Spirit beareth witneſſe with our ſpirit, that we are the children of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is then a prepoſterous courſe of many (who are more forward to call <hi>Father, Father,</hi>
               <note place="margin">We may not begin with Predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> then to <hi>doe the will of this Father, which is in heauen)</hi> that they bend their wits how to breake open the cloſet of diuine Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and to ſearch the <hi>record</hi> of eternall <hi>adoption,</hi> yet take no heed to <hi>ſeeke</hi> out, or <hi>looke</hi> in the <hi>patent</hi> of <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation,</hi> which is, or ſhould bee about them.
<note place="margin">But with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation.</note> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it ſtandeth for an infallible <hi>maxime,</hi> that whatſoeuer ſonne God <hi>adopteth</hi> beforetime, he <hi>begetteth</hi> alſo in time (1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3.) ſo that he is not only <hi>choſen</hi> of God, <hi>(Eph.</hi> 1.4.) but <hi>borne</hi> of God (1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.9) not of his <hi>nature</hi> indeed, but of his <hi>grace:</hi> and ſo borne of grace, that hee is <hi>made partaker of the godly nature,</hi> (2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4.) although not of the nature of diuine <hi>Eſſence,</hi> yet of the nature of <hi>god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly qualities,</hi> holineſſe, righteouſneſſe, knowledge, &amp;c. whereby a godly ſonne <hi>reſembleth</hi> God his Father; howbeit, in moſt <hi>vnequall</hi> proportion, as little <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyanax</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:25202:7"/>did his great Father <hi>Hector:</hi>
               <q>
                  <hi>Sic oculos, ſicille manus, ſic or a ferebat.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>In this <hi>generation,</hi> or rather <hi>regeneration,</hi> God is our <hi>Father begetting</hi> vs, (<hi>verſ.</hi> 3. of this chapter) the Church his Spouſe is our <hi>Mother</hi> conceiuing vs, <hi>(Gal.</hi> 4.26.) the meanes is the <hi>immortall ſeed of the Word (infra, verſ.</hi> 23.) and the <hi>vitall ſpirit</hi> that giueth life to this ſeed is the holy ſpirit of God. <hi>Spiritus intus alit:</hi> It <hi>is the ſpirit that giueth life, Ioh.</hi> 6.63.</p>
            <p>Being thus begotten, wee are <hi>borne</hi> of God in <hi>mercie, nurſed</hi> of God in <hi>knowledge, nurtured</hi> of God in <hi>grace,</hi> and haue <hi>inheritance</hi> with God in <hi>glorie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whoſoeuer now will be ſure,
<note place="margin">How to be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of our aſſurance.</note> that his euidence for this inheritance is <hi>firme</hi> and indefeazible, and that he is none of that great number, who are wont to be both <hi>artificiall</hi> in forging within their braines a ſeale of faith, in ſhew much counterfaiting that of Gods handy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke; and hauing forged it, are <hi>prompt</hi> and liberall to ſcale to their credulous hearts, ſome probable ſecuritie of the land of promiſe, without any approueable ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity for the promiſe of that Land: let him ſee, whether with his owne ſeale of faith, there be ioyned the ſeale of Gods Spirit; which he ſhall diſcerne from all counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faits, by the print thereof, <hi>viz.</hi> the New man, <hi>totally</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed, in reſpect of his <hi>partes,</hi> albeit in regard of <hi>degrees,</hi> he haue but an <hi>imperfect perfection.</hi> For if he can ſee in himſelfe the <hi>Image</hi> of God in a <hi>waxie</hi> heart (though blemiſhed and bruiſed by ſinfull corruption) and the <hi>ſuperſcription</hi> of the holy Ghoſt, in a holy (though not wholly compleate) renouation, in vnfained (howbeit not vnſtained) ſanctification; hee hath hence <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenticall</hi> proofe for his ſonneſhip by <hi>regeneration,</hi> and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:25202:7"/>thereby for his ſonneſhip by <hi>adoption,</hi> which claſping faſt, hee can boldly aſcend in prayer to heauen, and preſſing home to the Throne of grace, <hi>cry, Abba Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus we call, and onely thus may wee rightly <hi>call him Father, who without reſpect of perſons, iudgeth according to euery mans worke;</hi> which is the ſecond branch of the doctrine, propoſing God with the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of a <hi>Iudge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which iudgeth,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] And doth he now iudge? there are two ſorts of Gods iudgement:<note place="margin">The time of Gods Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Preſent,</hi> by his <hi>diſpoſing</hi> iuſtice in ordering of the world.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>Future,</hi> by his <hi>rewarding</hi> iuſtice at the ending of the world.</item>
            </list>
            <p>His preſent iudgements are alwaies righteous, <hi>(Pſalme</hi> 119.75.) yet not alwaies ſeene to bee right <hi>according to euery mans workes,</hi> ſeeing that heere good men often ſuffer euill, while the euill enioy good: but that <hi>laſt</hi> iudgement ſhall not onely it ſelfe be mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly iuſt, but alſo manifeſt the iuſtice of all his former proceedings; whence it is called <hi>the declaration of the iuſt iudgement of God, Rom.</hi> 2.5.</p>
            <p>This future iudgement is here timed as preſent, according to the vſe of Scripture, to ſignifie,
<list>
                  <item>1. A <hi>certainty</hi> that it ſhall bee, as ſurely as if it were preſent, <hi>Ezechiel.</hi> 7.6. <hi>The end is come, the end is come, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. In this certainty an <hi>vncertainty</hi> when it ſhal bee, that for any thing wee know, it may bee preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>The day of the Lord commeth as a thiefe in the night.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:25202:8"/>
                  <item>3.
<note place="margin">The manner.</note> In this vncertainty, a <hi>certainty</hi> that it will not bee long, but muſt bee expected preſently. <hi>Behold, I come quickly (Reuel.</hi> 22.12) <hi>and my reward is with me, to giue euery man according to his worke.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Without reſpect, &amp;c.]</hi> His throne of iudgement is here kept vpright by two Supporters,
<note place="margin">1. Impartiall.</note>
               <list>
                  <item>1. An impartiall eie, <hi>without reſpect of perſons.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. A proportioning hand, <hi>according to euery mans worke.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſpect of perſons</hi> iſſueth commonly, eyther from <hi>affection,</hi> or <hi>opinion:</hi> affection being <hi>partiall,</hi> willingly peruerteth; opinion being <hi>preiudicate,</hi> vnwittingly ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth. Now who can ſuſpect partiality in Gods affection, that heareth ſo often inculcated in the diuine Oracles, that <hi>Rich</hi> or <hi>Poore, Prieſt</hi> or <hi>People, Iew</hi> or <hi>Gentile,</hi> not their perſons, but their doings ſhall be regarded and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded? <hi>Tros Tyriuſque mihi nullo diſcrimine agetur. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation and anguiſh vpon euery ſoule that doth euill, the Iew firſt, and alſo the Grecian; but to euery man that doth good, glory, honour, and peace, to the Iew firſt, and alſo to the Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian; for there is no reſpect of perſons with God, Rom.</hi> 2.9.10.11.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, who can imagine, that a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudicate opinion can blind thoſe <hi>eyes of fire (Reu.</hi> 1.14.) that ſtay not vpon the vizour and outſide of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall profeſſion, but pierce thorow the inſide and heart of euery priſoner at his Barre? All the world <hi>before his throne is a ſea of glaſſe, like vnto Chryſtall (Reu.</hi> 4.6.) tranſparent and perſpicuous to the ſupreme Iudge, who <hi>will inlighten the hidden darkeneſſe</hi> (1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5.) <hi>and make the counſels of the heart manifeſt;</hi> and is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:25202:8"/>not onely an eye witneſſe of all outward paſſages, but alſo <hi>ſearcheth the heart and trieth the reines (Iere.</hi> 17.10.) <hi>euen to giue euery man according to his wayes, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the fruit of his works;</hi> which is the other ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Gods tribunall, <hi>viz.</hi> a proportioning hand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>According to euery mans worke.]</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to works.</note> This word <hi>accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> implieth a double regard of workes in the finall iudgement:
<list>
                  <item>1. According to their <hi>quality,</hi> whether they bee ſtraight or crooked, good or bad.</item>
                  <item>2. According to their <hi>quantity,</hi> whether they bee great or ſmall, many or few.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>quality</hi> of euery mans workes ſhall bee tried,
<note place="margin">1. According to their quality.</note> whether they be ſtraight or crooked, by laying them to that <hi>rule of righteouſneſſe</hi> which God hath giuen him, <hi>viz.</hi> The Law of <hi>Nature</hi> to the Gentiles, the Law <hi>writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten</hi> for the Iewes, and the <hi>Goſpell</hi> for vs Chriſtians: all which appeareth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.12.15.16. The two Lawes, being indeed one (for the naturall Law is the <hi>morall infolded,</hi> and the morall Law is the <hi>naturall vnfolded)</hi> they haue both one iniunction, <hi>Doe this, and liue;</hi> the Goſpell another, <hi>Beleeue, and liue.</hi> The Law exacteth the perfect <hi>righteouſnees of works:</hi> the Goſpel accepteth for perfect the <hi>righteouſnees of faith, Ro.</hi> 3.20.21. &amp; 4.13.</p>
            <p>But heere lieth a great blocke in the way:
<note place="margin">For workes are regarded.</note> for if we be ſaued <hi>by faith, and not by workes,</hi> as that, and other places of Scripture doe teach vs, how then is this true, that <hi>Euery man ſhall be iudged according to his workes?</hi> at this blocke both <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Libertines</hi> haue ſo ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, that they haue tumbled into errour, the one vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the right hand, of <hi>Merite,</hi> the other on the left hand, of <hi>Licentiouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:25202:9"/>
            <p>For the clearing of the way betweene them, and the whole doctrine of faith and workes, let vs conceiue of two Courts wherein God proceedeth in iudging vs. Of
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Iuſtification</hi> in this life.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Remuneration</hi> after death.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>For the opening hereof,
<note place="margin">Although not in Iuſtification.</note> wee may imagine how the penitent ſinner commeth into the Court of <hi>Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> deſiring to be approued of God, and accepted in his fight: but ſeeing exact righteouſneſſe to bee there ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted, and that none are receiued, but ſuch as are pure and perfect, hee ſhrinketh backe, and lamenteth his owne wretched plight, that dares not appeare in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, being all ouergrowne with a ſinfull <hi>leprouſie,</hi> and can but cry,
<note place="margin">Opera non prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedunt iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candum:</note> 
               <hi>Enter not into iudgement with thy ſeruant, O Lord.</hi> But anon perceiuing, that Chriſt, the Lord Iudge his Sonne, hath plenary righteouſneſſe, not for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe (for being the <hi>naturall Sonne,</hi> hee needeth not to buy his Fathers acceptation) but for his <hi>retainers;</hi> and hearing him call <hi>(Reuel.</hi> 3.18.) <hi>I counſel thee to buy of me white raiment, that thou maieſt be clothed, and that thy fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy nakedneſſe doe not appeare;</hi> hee proſtrateth himſelfe at the feet of this heauenly <hi>Clothier,</hi> and hauing no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, nor <hi>merites,</hi> to buy, he falleth to begging in the humble <hi>ſupplicat</hi> of a liuely faith, <hi>Lord, if thou wilt, thou canſt make me cleane.</hi> This ſuit being effectuall, hath an anſwere as comfortable, <hi>I will, bee thou cleane.</hi> Then waſhing away the leprous ſpottes of his ſinnes with the bloud which hee ſhed, and clothing his nakedneſſe with the merites which hee wrought for vs, hee thus preſenteth him to his Father, and the Father accepteth him for righteous, and regiſtreth him among his Saints. And this is the ſumme of our <hi>Iuſtification.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:25202:9"/>
            <p>But before this bleſſed Sauiour,
<note place="margin">Sed ſequuntur iuſtificatum.</note> diſmiſſe this healed ſinner,</p>
            <q>
               <l>—<hi>Cynthius aurem</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>vellit, &amp; admonuit,</hi>—</l>
            </q>
            <p>Hee roundeth him in the eare, and ſcholeth him for keeping a diet: <hi>Behold, thou art made whole, ſinne no more, lest worſe betide thee: but goe, and offer for thy clenſing, thoſe things which Moſes commanded (Mark.</hi> 1.44.) Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I haue freed thee from the <hi>curſe</hi> of the Law, yet thou in thankfulneſſe art ſtill obliged to the <hi>duty</hi> of the Law, <hi>that being thus deliuered, thou maiſt ſerue God without feare, in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe before him all the dayes of thy life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou canſt not indeed doe ſo well as thou <hi>ſhouldeſt;</hi> but be carefull to doe ſo well as thou <hi>canſt.</hi> What thou canſt not doe ſo well as thou ſhouldeſt, the <hi>white raiment</hi> of righteouſneſſe, which I haue giuen thee, ſhal <hi>couer,</hi> and it ſhall not be puniſhed: and what thou doeſt ſo well as thou canſt, the ſame white garment ſhall make to ſhew more white, and it ſhall be rewarded.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee,
<note place="margin">The diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion granted to the beleeuer</note> how faith hauing procured a <hi>qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>grace,</hi> a <hi>diſpenſation</hi> is granted for workes: that
<list>
                  <item>1. Our euill deeds, though <hi>perfectly</hi> euill, ſhall be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, as waſhed and drowned in the <hi>bloud</hi> of Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>2. Our good deeds, though <hi>imperfectly good,</hi> ſhall be accepted as decked and beautified with the <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe</hi> of Chriſt.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And comming vnto God henceforth in the <hi>fragrant</hi> raiment of our elder brother (as <hi>Iacob</hi> in <hi>Eſau, Gen.</hi> 27.) he ſmelleth a ſweet ſauour from vs, is pleaſed to feed vpon, and to reliſh that which wee bring him, and ſo <hi>bleſſeth</hi> vs, and we <hi>ſhall be bleſſed.</hi> And as lame <hi>Mephibo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:25202:10"/>was entertained at King <hi>Dauids</hi> Table, for his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Ionathans</hi> ſake, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 9.7. ſo God admitteth our <hi>halting</hi> obedience for his Sonnes ſake, to make vs parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of his heauenly Table.</p>
            <p>Now as the Court of iuſtification regardeth onely <hi>faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Yet in remu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration workes are reſpected.</note> in making him righteous, that is not ſuch; ſo the Court of <hi>remuneration</hi> will reſpect <hi>workes,</hi> in <hi>declaring</hi> him righteous, which hath beene made ſuch. For it ſtandeth for a <hi>principle,</hi> that whoſoeuer truely belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth well, endeuoureth duely to <hi>liue well;</hi> and euery one that is <hi>graced</hi> of God by <hi>iuſtification,</hi> doth ſtriue to <hi>glorifie</hi> God by <hi>ſantification,</hi> and with the healed <hi>Cripple, Act.</hi> 3.8. <hi>followeth walking, and leaping, and praiſing God:</hi> it is taken for a manifeſt concluſion in iudgement, that the faith, which is <hi>fruitleſſe,</hi> is alſo <hi>faithleſſe,</hi> like a painted fire, that is indeed no fire, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>Colorem,</hi> and not <hi>calorem,</hi> ſome <hi>colour</hi> of perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but no heat of deuotion.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing the laſt iudgement will bee vpon the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Theater of the world, in view of all men, who vſe not to diue into the heart of man, to ſee his <hi>faith,</hi> but onely looke in through the lettice of his <hi>behauiour;</hi> nor can iudge of the <hi>tree</hi> by the inward <hi>ſappe,</hi> but by the outward fruit, the <hi>Lord</hi> will <hi>manifeſt</hi> the integrity of that iudgement, not by <hi>inuiſible</hi> faith, but by <hi>viſible</hi> works; that all ſoules may aſſent &amp; acknowledge, how they are moſt iuſtly diſtinguiſhed in their <hi>recompence,</hi> that were ſo different in their <hi>liues,</hi> when <hi>Euery one recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the things he hath done in his body, whether they be good or euill,</hi> 2. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 5.10.</p>
            <p>To conclude this point then: all men being iudged by <hi>rule,</hi> according to the <hi>quality</hi> of their workes, ſhall
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:25202:10"/>be ſeparated with one generall <hi>diuiſion,</hi> right from croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, good from bad, ſheepe from goates: and their <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> will be diuided accordingly (as <hi>Eſa.</hi> 3.) <hi>It ſhall be well with the iuſt, for they ſhall eate the fruit of their workes;</hi> and <hi>Woe to the wicked, it ſhall be euill with him, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of his hands ſhall be giuen him.</hi> For the one ſort a gracious call, <hi>Come ye bleſſed;</hi> and for the other a dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>mittimus, Goe ye curſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>quantity</hi> of workes is to be ſcanned two wayes.
<note place="margin">2. According to their quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity.</note> By
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Tale</hi> for their number.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Scale</hi> for their weight.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>number,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euill workers.</note> the euill workes (wherein are compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended the <hi>words</hi> and <hi>thoughts)</hi> of the <hi>wicked,</hi> ſhall be caſt vp by expedite <hi>Arithmatike,</hi> and the tranſgreſſions,
<note place="margin">For number.</note> which now they daily augment, by <hi>Addition, Multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> and continuall <hi>Progreſsion in ſinne,</hi> without any <hi>Subſtraction</hi> by repentance, ſhall then bee ſummed vp into a <hi>totall,</hi> and a proportionable number of number<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe paines apportioned vnto them altogether. <hi>As much as ſhee liued in pleaſure, ſo much giue you to her tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ſorrow, Reu.</hi> 18.7.</p>
            <p>For <hi>weight;</hi> in the ballance of Iuſtice,
<note place="margin">For weight.</note> will he poize the <hi>grieuouſneſſe</hi> of their ſinnes: which as they carry <hi>ſeuerall</hi> weight in their different <hi>natures</hi> (ſome being <hi>grauiora,</hi> more heauy then others) ſo alſo are they ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauated by <hi>circumſtances,</hi> as occaſions of <hi>information</hi> neglected, or prouocations to <hi>reformation</hi> reiected: all which being put together <hi>(ſubſtance</hi> and <hi>circumſtance)</hi> in <hi>one ſcale,</hi> the <hi>other</hi> ſhal haue puniſhments to counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poize them all. <hi>The ſeruant, that knew not his maſters will,</hi> ſhall bee excuſed <hi>à tanto,</hi> though not <hi>à toto;</hi> his igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance muſt <hi>be beaten,</hi> but being not wilfull, <hi>with fewer
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:25202:11"/>ſtripes:</hi> but he <hi>that knew it, and did it not,</hi> or would not know to do it, he <hi>ſhall be beaten with many ſtripes, Luk.</hi> 12.47.48. Hard, alas, wil it be with the <hi>Heathen,</hi> that walked to hell in darkneſſe, while their ſtarre-light of <hi>reaſon</hi> could not diſcouer the way to heauen: but it will bee harder with <hi>carnall profeſſors,</hi> who in the Sun-ſhine of the Goſpell, being ſhewed the narrow way that leadeth to bliſſe, yet gallop along the broad way to deſtruction. <hi>Woe,</hi> and double woe vnto ſuch; for if many of the Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels had beene partakers of the ſame good meanes and motiues, they would a great while agone haue <hi>repented, ſitting in ſackcloth and aſhes. Therefore it ſhall bee eaſier for Infidels at the iudgement, then for ſuch, Luke</hi> 10.13.14.</p>
            <p>In like manner,
<note place="margin">Good workes. By tale.</note> the good deedes of good men are to be ſurueighed both by <hi>tale,</hi> and by <hi>ſcale.</hi> By <hi>tale;</hi> for God doth keepe an Inuentorie of them: he hath a <hi>Bottle</hi> for our <hi>teares,</hi> (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 56.) a <hi>Bagge</hi> for our <hi>almes</hi> (<hi>Luke</hi> 12.) and a <hi>Booke</hi> for our <hi>good workes,</hi> (<hi>Reu.</hi> 20.) <hi>God is not vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, that he ſhould forget any of our good workes, Heb.</hi> 6.10. Euery godly deed is a <hi>flower</hi> ſent vp to heauen, of which our Iudge doth plot vs a neuer-fading <hi>Garland</hi> of glory; and the more flowers, the greater garland, for <hi>He that ſoweth plenteouſly, ſhall reape plenteouſly.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.6.</p>
            <p>By <hi>ſcale;</hi>
               <note place="margin">By ſcale.</note> a weightier good done, hath a weightier reward giuen. <hi>Thou ſhalt reſt and ſtand vp in thy lot, at the end of the dayes,</hi> ſaid the Angell to <hi>Daniel, Chap.</hi> 12.13. Happy and thrice happy is euery one that hath any <hi>lot</hi> in heauen: the <hi>leaſt of all Saints</hi> may ſing in the Quire of all Saints, <hi>My lot is fallen in a pleaſant ground, I haue a goodly heritage</hi> (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.6) and yet herein may be diſparity: there is (<hi>Dan.</hi> 12.3.) one general lot, for them <hi>that be wiſe, to ſhine as the brightneſſe of the firmament; but
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:25202:11"/>they that turne many to righteouſnes,</hi> haue a ſpeciall lot, to ſhine <hi>as the ſtars for euer and euer.</hi> Now as all <hi>ſtars</hi> are brighter then the <hi>firmament,</hi> ſo alſo <hi>one ſtar differeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another in glory, &amp; ſo is the reſurrection of the dead,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. Euery workeman of God, though his worke be not worth his meat and drinke, being an <hi>vnprofitable ſeruant</hi> (<hi>Luk.</hi> 17.10.) ſhall yet haue the <hi>penny</hi> of eternall life gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him for wages. Euery one his <hi>penny,</hi> that is, <hi>fulneſſe</hi> of ioy, ſo that he which hath leaſt, neither repineth for himſelfe, as hauing too little, nor enuieth at all others, as hauing too much. Yet with this <hi>fulneſſe</hi> there ſtand ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall <hi>degrees</hi> according to the ſeuerall degrees of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>grace,</hi> by which they are diuerſly capable of future glorie. Some like <hi>Gomers,</hi> ſome like <hi>Ephahs,</hi> ſome as pintes, ſome as pottles; all ſhall bee full according to their meaſure, with as much happines as each can wiſh. Al like in <hi>ſatiety,</hi> but not alike in <hi>parity</hi> of bliſſe; for, <hi>euery one ſhall receiue his reward according to his labor,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.8.</p>
            <p>Nor doth this any way vphold the doctrine of <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Yet no merit.</note> which arrogating too much to our owne good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in deſeruing, doth derogate as much from Gods goodneſſe in free giuing. Farre be it from vs to imagine, that our Lord and Maſter dealeth with vs in <hi>commuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue</hi> Iuſtice, as giuing vs, (<hi>Matth.</hi> 20.8.9.) a <hi>pennie</hi> for a pennie-worth of worke; as if the <hi>wages</hi> were <hi>not counted by fauour, but by debt, Rom.</hi> 4.4. It is indeed <hi>giuen as wages;</hi> but as <hi>wages giuen,</hi> not earned; it is a <hi>reward,</hi> but <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3.24. <hi>the reward of the inheritance,</hi> to them that <hi>ſerue the Lord Chriſt:</hi> diſpenſed as vnto ſeruants, <hi>a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of ſeruing the Lord,</hi> but conferred as vnto <hi>Sonnes,</hi> for our portion of <hi>inheritance.</hi> Euery one hath his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, not for his labour (for we cannot deſerue it)
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:25202:12"/>yet <hi>according</hi> to his labour, by a due and equall inequali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: <hi>due,</hi> only by <hi>promiſe,</hi> as a portion of <hi>grace</hi> (<hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.8.) yet <hi>duly</hi> performed by <hi>proportion</hi> of Iuſtice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paſſe the time]</hi> The <hi>Vſe</hi> whereto this doctrine leuel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, is to breed <hi>feare:</hi> for the better impreſſion whereof, the Apoſtle toucheth by the way two <hi>motiues,</hi> giuing vs an inkling of the gliding, and ſlippery ſtate of our life, as being
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Tranſitorie,</hi> but a <hi>time,</hi> whoſe being is <hi>in fluxu,</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but a <hi>fleeting</hi> and <hi>paſsing.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Fickle,</hi> being <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> not <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a commorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but no habitation; a <hi>ſoiourning,</hi> (as the new Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation) rather then a dwelling; or at leaſt ſuch a <hi>dwelling,</hi> as of <hi>Tenants at will,</hi> that ſtandeth vpon moſt <hi>vncertaine</hi> termes: <hi>Paſſe the time of your dwelling here in feare.</hi> But onely glauncing at theſe, <hi>feare</hi> is the marke whereunto this Text aimeth.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Among many ſorts whereof,
<note place="margin">Feare three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold.</note> we may take notice of theſe three:
<list>
                  <item>1. Infernall, in horrour of puniſhment.</item>
                  <item>2. Criminall, vnder the burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of guiltines.</item>
                  <item>3. Filiall, in duty of grace.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>infernall</hi> is a deſperate feare, when hell gnawing vpon the damned ſoule, ſhe lieth trembling, like vnto a <hi>Partridge,</hi> while the Hawke plumeth her; or a <hi>Sheepe,</hi> while the Wolfe deuoureth her, which dieth fearing, and feareth dying. The <hi>Criminall</hi> is a <hi>perplexed</hi> feare, the ſhaking Palſy of a guiltie conſcience, fearing to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer euill for doing euill. The <hi>Filiall</hi> is a <hi>reuerent</hi> feare, keeping the heart in awe from doing euill againſt God, that hath done ſo much good for vs.</p>
            <p>This laſt is peculiar to the Elect, and is abſolutely good; the <hi>firſt</hi> is proper to the Damned, and is alwaies
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:25202:12"/>
               <hi>naught:</hi> the <hi>middle</hi> is middle betweene both, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times good, and ſometimes euill, according to the <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect</hi> in which, and the <hi>end</hi> to which it worketh. In the <hi>Reprobate,</hi> a criminall feare is the portall of hell, the threſhold of infernall feare, and is meerely <hi>ſeruile:</hi> in the <hi>choſen,</hi> it is the entry to repentance, an introduction to filiall feare. In the <hi>wicked,</hi> it is the firſt biting of the <hi>worme</hi> of conſcience, which in hell will euer gnaw, and <hi>neuer die:</hi> as in <hi>Cain, Geneſ.</hi> 4. In the <hi>godly,</hi> it is a biting alſo of conſcience worme, <hi>remorſus;</hi> but by this byting, his biting is preuented: <hi>remorſe</hi> bringeth foorth <hi>amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and the daughter eateth vp the mother: it <hi>cauſeth repentance vnto ſaluation, not to be repented of</hi> (2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.10) like a ſudden affright, which cureth an Ague, as in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.10.</p>
            <p>This feare is a good Vſher to <hi>enter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Initiall feare.</note> but no good Tutour to <hi>perfect</hi> a Chriſtian: for when the <hi>Law, our School-maſter</hi> (<hi>Galat.</hi> 3.24.25.) hath plaid his part with the rod of terrour, to whippe vs to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> being come into his high and Free-ſchole, we muſt learne to learne, more for <hi>loue</hi> of learning, then for <hi>feare</hi> of beating. This pricking feare doth very good ſeruice, as a ſharpe <hi>needle</hi> to make way for the thred of loue to follow; whereby God and man being <hi>ſowed</hi> together, the <hi>thred</hi> holdeth, the <hi>needle</hi> is taken away. Thus feare hauing drawne in loue, <hi>loue</hi> being growne <hi>perfect, caſteth out feare,</hi> 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.18.</p>
            <p>But as it caſteth out one feare,
<note place="margin">Filiall feare.</note> ſo it bringeth in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>Serue the Lord without feare,</hi> ſaith <hi>Zachary, Luk.</hi> 1 74. yet <hi>ſerue the Lord in feare,</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid, Pſalm.</hi> 2.11. ſerue him without that <hi>ſeruile</hi> feare, that abhorreth the <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment,</hi> more then the offence; but ſerue him with
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:25202:13"/>that <hi>filiall</hi> feare, which deteſteth the <hi>offence</hi> more then the puniſhment.</p>
            <p>I ſay [the offence <hi>more</hi> then the puniſhment] becauſe a good Chriſtian may in due order caſt an eye on both.
<note place="margin">Compounded.</note> And if we follow the ſtreame of feare in this Text back to his ſprings, we ſee it ariſeth from two heads: 1. God is our <hi>Father;</hi> there ſpringeth vp the feare of his <hi>mercies, There is mercy with thee, that thou maiſt be feared, Pſalm.</hi> 130.4. Secondly, God is a <hi>Iudge;</hi> and thence riſeth the feare of his <hi>iudgements:</hi> for <hi>it is a fearefull thing to fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of the liuing God, Heb.</hi> 10.31. the feare of his mercies, is the maine ſpring and <hi>predominant,</hi> whereby we principally abhorre the <hi>fault:</hi> the feare of his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments is the leſſer ſpring and <hi>ſubordinate,</hi> whereby in a ſecond place, we ſhunne the puniſhment. Looking vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God, as our moſt gracious <hi>Father,</hi> wee bee, or at leaſt ſhould be, both <hi>ſtudious</hi> of weldoing, becauſe it pleaſeth him, though there were no <hi>heauen</hi> to reward vs; and <hi>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous</hi> of ill-doing, becauſe it offendeth him, though there were no <hi>hell</hi> to terrifie vs: but, for that dulneſſe and ſecuritie are ſo ready to ouertake vs, he preſenteth himſelfe on the other ſide as a <hi>Iudge,</hi> holding out in his right hand, <hi>reward,</hi> in his left hand, <hi>puniſhment,</hi> that with theſe two <hi>ſpurres,</hi> he might both ſtirre vp him that ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth ſtill, and driue him faſter, that is already on his way.</p>
            <p>The firſt place in our hearts muſt be taken vp for the feare of God as a <hi>Father,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Of Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</note> ariſing from the ſenſe of his <hi>mercy:</hi> and this feare is not the mother of diſtruſt, but the <hi>daughter</hi> of <hi>faith, Pſalm.</hi> 5.7. <hi>In the multitude of thy mercies, I will goe into thy houſe,</hi> (there Faith the mother leadeth the way) <hi>and will worſhip in feare, &amp;c.</hi> there the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:25202:13"/>daughter followeth. This feare is not the daughter of painefull anxiety, but the <hi>mother</hi> of ioyfull <hi>alacrity, Pſal.</hi> 2 11. <hi>Reioyce before him in feare.</hi> This feare is not a ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uall, but a <hi>ſiſter of loue,</hi> going ſo louingly hand in hand, that none loue God better then they that feare him moſt, none feare him more, then they which loue him beſt.</p>
            <p>The feare of God as a <hi>Iudge,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Of Caution.</note> ariſing from the medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his <hi>iudgements,</hi> may, and muſt haue his place too: and when the former feare is made <hi>Steward</hi> of the heart, this latter may take his place, as an excellent <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> to examine euery thought, before it giue paſſage. This is not a feare of diffidence, for it leadeth in <hi>confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, Pſalm.</hi> 41. <hi>Many ſhall ſee it, and feare, and ſhall put their truſt in the Lord.</hi> Firſt feare, then <hi>truſt.</hi> It is not a feare of perplexity, but of <hi>caution, Pro.</hi> 14.27. <hi>The feare of the Lord is a welſpring of life, to auoide the ſnares of death.</hi> This Porters office is to keepe out <hi>ſecuritie, licentiouſnes,</hi> and ſuch other <hi>vagrants,</hi> as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Tremble and ſin not:</hi> againſt theſe it ſtandeth in the dore of the heart, like the <hi>Cherub</hi> in the gate of Paradiſe, brandiſhing the flaming ſword of Gods heauy iudgements, in threatning death, hell, torments, &amp;c. It maketh of theſe, armour of proofe againſt ſinne; quencheth the fire of luſt in the flame of euerlaſting fire, and maketh the fornace of hell, a cooler of his paſſions. That it may flie from it, it flieth vnto it; and when he moſt flieth from it, then he findeth it the ſafeſt refuge, and the more hee thus feareth it, the leſſe cauſe there is to feare it.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſeuerall feares thus riſing from ſeuerall heads,
<note place="margin">Their vnion.</note> 
               <hi>father</hi> and <hi>iudge,</hi> meete together here in the ſtreame of one <hi>compound,</hi> and wel-tempered feare both of <hi>mercy</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:25202:14"/>and <hi>iudgement:</hi> a feare mixed of that <hi>honour</hi> due to a <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and that <hi>feare</hi> due to our <hi>Lord, Malach.</hi> 1.6. a feare, that is both <hi>louing</hi> and <hi>wary.</hi> We may call it an <hi>awfull loue,</hi> or a <hi>louing awe:</hi> and in this feare, wee muſt <hi>paſſe the time of our dwelling here.</hi> Which, how it iſſueth from the premiſſes, as the <hi>Vſe</hi> from the <hi>Doctrine,</hi> wee muſt now conſider, and ſo deſcend from explication to appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, from <hi>lightening</hi> our minds, to <hi>heate</hi> our affections.</p>
            <p>And that we might be throughly heated with godly feare, the Apoſtle here placeth vs betweene the <hi>Sun</hi> and the <hi>fire:</hi>
               <note place="margin">For Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly loue.</note> on the one ſide, God a <hi>Father,</hi> a comfortable <hi>Sunne-ſhine</hi> of mercy; on the other ſide, God a <hi>Iudge,</hi> a ſcalding <hi>Fire</hi> of iuſtice. In the Sunne-ſhine of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy we may obſerue a twofold brightneſſe,
<list>
                  <item>1. In him, in his <hi>direct</hi> beames, proceeding of his owne goodneſſe.</item>
                  <item>2. From him, in their incidence on vs, <hi>reflecting</hi> to our <hi>happineſſe.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The immanent <hi>ſplendour</hi> of his diuine goodneſſe,
<note place="margin">1. In being our Father.</note> if we ſhall compare it with the <hi>candle</hi> of humane kindnes, what incomparable difference ſhall we find! It is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily eſteemed to be a ſingular fauour, when a rich man that hath no ſonne of his owne, adopteth ſome neere <hi>kinſman</hi> or <hi>friend,</hi> whom he moſt affecteth for his good <hi>behauiour.</hi> But not any one of theſe motiues haue any place with God. Did he <hi>lacke ſonnes</hi> and heires of his happines? No: beſides his naturall Sonne, many mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of <hi>Angels</hi> ſtand like <hi>Oliue branches round about his table:</hi> yet ſuch is his loue, hee would adopt vs. Were we any <hi>kinne</hi> vnto him? No: we came all of another ſtock, and might <hi>ſay to corruption, Thou are my father, and to the wormes, Thou art my mother, Iob</hi> 17.14. and yet ſuch
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:25202:14"/>was his goodnes, hee would adopt vs. If not his Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, were we then his <hi>friends?</hi> No:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> we were not only <hi>aliants</hi> &amp; ſtrangers, but <hi>enemies,</hi> euen from the wombe; <hi>Thy father was an Ammorite, and thy mother a Hittite, Ezech.</hi> 16.3. and yet ſuch was his goodneſſe, hee would be our Father.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Did we then enchaine his affection vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs by our good <hi>demeanour?</hi> No, no: for vntill he made vs his ſonnes by new birth, wee ran the ſinfull <hi>prodigals</hi> race; and if with him, in the confidence of Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes we could dare to ſay, <hi>Father,</hi> yet in conſcience of our owne naughtines, we muſt needs adde, <hi>I haue ſinned againſt heauen, and againſt thee; I am no more worthy to bee called thy ſonne:</hi> and yet, yet notwithſtanding all this, ſuch is his goodnes ſtill, ſtill be would be our <hi>Father. O Lord, what</hi> diddeſt thou ſee in <hi>man, that thou ſo regardeſt him, or the ſonne of man,</hi> that thou ſhouldeſt make him thy ſonne! the brightnes of this bountie is ſo glittering and glorious, that it beateth back our weake ſight from beholding it; ſo that returning our dazled cies downe to our ſelues, we can but cry out with the <hi>Apoſtle; O the depth!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But although we cannot, like ſoaring Eagles,
<note place="margin">2. In ſhewing himſelfe our Father.</note> dare the ſhining Sunne in the face, yet may wee obſerue his <hi>inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> vpon our ſelues. Obſerue it indeed we may: but as the beames of the Sunne, ſo Gods fauours vpon his children, are not to be compriſed either in number or meaſure. They extend <hi>in infinitum,</hi> and if wee attempt to meaſure them, they grow in meaſuring: they may be diuided <hi>in ſemper diuiſibilia,</hi> and if wee aſſay to num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber them, they increaſe in numbering. Onely this in generall: ſo farre as our heauenly Father tranſcendeth our earthly parents in excellence (which is a compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:25202:15"/>there being no proportion betweene <hi>finite</hi> and <hi>infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite</hi>) ſo farre hee ſurmounteth alſo in the exact perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of all fatherly offices, as namely (to giue a taſte of ſome amongſt all, and of all by thoſe ſome) in fatherly <hi>affection, inſtruction, correction, protection,</hi> and <hi>prouiſion.</hi> In fatherly <hi>affection,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> who ſo kind? <hi>Eſa.</hi> 49.15. <hi>Can a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man forget her child, and not haue compaſsion on the ſon of her wombe? though they ſhould forget, yet will not I forget thee.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> In fatherly <hi>inſtruction,</hi> who ſo diligent? <hi>Ier.</hi> 31.31. <hi>I will put my Law in their inward parts, and will write it in their hearts, and I will be their God, and they ſhal be my people.</hi> In fatherly <hi>correction,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> who ſo louing? <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.10. The fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of our bodies <hi>chaſten</hi> vs after <hi>their owne pleaſure,</hi> but the Father of ſpirits chaſteneth vs <hi>for our profit, that wee may be partakers of his holineſſe.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> In fatherly <hi>protection,</hi> who ſo carefull? <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.16.11. The Lord kept <hi>Iacob as the apple of his eie:</hi> as an <hi>Eagle</hi> ſteareth vp her neſt, <hi>flootereth</hi> ouer her birds, <hi>ſtretcheth</hi> out her wings, taketh them, and <hi>beareth</hi> them on her wings: <hi>ſo the Lord alone led him.</hi> In fatherly <hi>prouiſion,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> who ſo plentifull, both for preſent <hi>maintenance,</hi> and future <hi>inheritance?</hi> hee giueth for this life ſufficient <hi>maintenance, Luke</hi> 12.31. Your heauenly Father <hi>knoweth,</hi> that yee haue need of theſe things: but ſeeke ye after the Kingdome of God, and <hi>all theſe things</hi> ſhall be miniſtred vnto you. And for the life to come, a <hi>roiall inheritance, verſ.</hi> 32. Feare not, little flocke, it is your Fathers pleaſure to giue you the <hi>Kingdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now (beloued in the Lord) ſhould all this <hi>light</hi> be without <hi>heate?</hi>
               <note place="margin">A reuerent feare due.</note> are not our hearts more inſenſible then the ſtones, if they warme not? more frozen then ice, if they <hi>melt</hi> not, in ſo cleare, ſo feruent a Sun-ſhine? who that hath the feeling of a child of God, can chooſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:25202:15"/>but proſtrate his ſoule in awfull obſequiouſneſſe, at the feet of him, whom thus we <hi>call Father?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet alas, if euery one ſhould examine one,
<note place="margin">But ill paid.</note> how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of vs here preſent, are bold to <hi>call him Father,</hi> and in the ſame breath as bold to diſpleaſe him! yea, <hi>&amp; eo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> ſo much the bolder, making his fatherly indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, a boulſter for our vnſonlike inſolence: and whereas <hi>there is mercy with him, that he may be feared,</hi> we on the contrary (vntoward children as we are) becauſe we hope to find <hi>mercy</hi> with him, we feare him not, but preſuming on impunity, make the leſſe conſcience of impietie. <hi>Doe yee ſo</hi> (ſaith <hi>Moſes, Deut.</hi> 32.6.) <hi>Do ye ſo reward the Lord, O fooliſh people and vnwiſe? is not hee thy Father, that hath bought thee, he that made and proportioned thee?</hi> With what face can we <hi>call him Father,</hi> with what heart can we thinke our ſelues to bee his ſonnes, feeling in vs no more feeling of deuout reuerence?</p>
            <p>The Sunbeames collected in a burning glaſſe,
<note place="margin">The reaſon,</note> kindle a fire vpon certaine conditions, <hi>viz.</hi> that the <hi>obiect</hi> be combuſtible, and apt to take fire, that it be held <hi>ſtill</hi> and ſteddy, and that it be in a iuſt diſtance, neither too <hi>farre</hi> off, nor yet too <hi>neere,</hi> but as the beames may beſt vnite their force: we are not without a <hi>burning glaſſe. I am come</hi> (ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Lu.</hi> 12.46.) to <hi>put fire on the earth;</hi> &amp; <hi>what is my deſire,</hi> but that it be kindled? Through him Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly loue ſhineth vpon vs: he ſtandeth as mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and vs, <hi>receiuing</hi> the beames of fauor, as his natural ſon, and <hi>tranſfuſing</hi> them altogether vpon vs, his adopted brethren. Being the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſo cleare a Sunſhine, and hauing ſo perfect a burning glaſſe, how comes it to paſſe that ſo many of vs continue ſo cold, ſo keycold? ſurely there is ſome defect, and failing in the conditions. Some
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:25202:16"/>hold the glaſſe <hi>too farre</hi> off, and thinke of the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God in Chriſt, but <hi>ſlightly</hi> and <hi>confuſedly:</hi> ſome hold it <hi>too neere,</hi> and being all vpon <hi>mercy, mercy,</hi> make remiſſion of ſinnes a plaiſter for <hi>preſumption</hi> in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: ſome hold it not ſtill by ſteddy and fixed medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but <hi>ſuperficially</hi> glaunce vpon it, by ſpurts and fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes: and ſome others are not of <hi>combuſtible</hi> matter; not ſo fit to be fired with the feare of his mercies, as to be feared with the fire of his iudgements.</p>
            <p>But we (beloued) as we deſire with ſolide comfort of ſoule to <hi>call him Father,</hi> that not onely our <hi>heads</hi> may imagine, or our <hi>tongues</hi> diſcourſe, but alſo our <hi>conſciences</hi> may feele, that wee are his children: Let the confluence of all his gracious beames of loue, heat our chill <hi>hearts,</hi> and our benummed hands with a deuout feare of his name: Let euery naming of this ſweet word <hi>Father,</hi> bee as the <hi>ſunne</hi> in his ſtrength to warme and reuiue our filiall obedience: ſo that as often as wee <hi>call him Father,</hi> ſo often wee remember, to <hi>paſſe the time of our dwelling here in feare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Here is good being;</hi> here I could <hi>build tabernacles,</hi> and paſſe my time and dwelling on Gods fatherly goodnes; for <hi>this is none other but the houſe of God, and gate of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">God is alſo a Iudge.</note> But me thinkes, with Saint, <hi>Iohn Reuel.</hi> 4 1.2. a <hi>Trumpet</hi> calleth me away, <hi>Come vp hither, and ſee things which muſt be done hereafter: a Throne is ſet, out of which proceed lightnings, and thundrings, and voyces,</hi> and a Iudge vpon the Throne, which <hi>without reſpect of perſons iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth according to euery mans worke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What a ſudden change is here,
<note place="margin">Yet no change</note> in the ſame verſe and line! but now a gracious <hi>Father,</hi> clothed all in the <hi>white</hi> robes of <hi>mercy,</hi> and preſently a ſeuere <hi>Iudge,</hi> attired in the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:25202:16"/>
               <hi>ſearlet</hi> robes of <hi>iuſtice?</hi> and is there indeed ſuch change in the <hi>immutable</hi> God? none at all: <hi>with him is no variablenes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In himſelfe.</note> 
               <hi>nor ſhaddow of change, Iam.</hi> 1.17 A piece of taffata, that is equally wrought of croſſe threds greene &amp; red, ſeemeth and is called <hi>changeable,</hi> yet is not changed; but one way as you look on it, it beareth vpon the red, another way it chiefly expreſſeth the greene: euen ſo in God there is an equall temper of mercie and iuſtice, whoſe threds doe ſeeme to croſſe each other:
<note place="margin">But in the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect.</note> and if you ſtand on the right hand among his <hi>ſonnes,</hi> the <hi>greene</hi> verdure of his goodneſſe carrieth away the ſight of his iudgements; but if you caſt your eye on the left ſide, as one of his <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners,</hi> the <hi>red fiery hiew of his Iuſtice,</hi> ſeemeth to drowne the ſight of mercie: Yea, the ſame day of Iudgement, <hi>Malac</hi> 4.1.2. proueth both a <hi>conſuming furnace,</hi> and a <hi>cheerefull ſun-ſhine:</hi> the obiect maketh the difference: <hi>It ſhall burne like an Ouen, and all that doe wickedly, ſhall bee ſtubble to burne therein:</hi> but <hi>verſe</hi> 2. vnto you <hi>that feare my name, ſhall the Sunne of righteouſneſſe ariſe, and ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhall be vnder his wings, &amp;c.</hi> Wherefore as we before turned our faces to the Sunne to warme vs, <hi>[ye call him Father]</hi> ſo let vs now turne about to the <hi>fire</hi> to heate vs; he <hi>[iudgeth without reſpect of perſons, &amp;c.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Thebans</hi> had amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g them the image of a Iudge ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting without <hi>eyes</hi> or <hi>hands;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The integritie of his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> no eyes that he might not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh perſons, friend from foe; no <hi>hands,</hi> that he might not receiue gifts to corrupt Iuſtice. But the iuſteſt Iudge of all the World is deciphered open-eyed and open-handed; his eyes open, not to procure, but to preuent reſpect of perſons; his <hi>hands</hi> open, not to take vndue bribes, but to giue due reward, <hi>Ier.</hi> 32.19. <hi>His eyes are open vpon all the wayes of the ſonnes of men, to giue to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:25202:17"/>one according to the fruit of his workes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Propoſe we then to our ſerious meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<note place="margin">The circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances.</note> the worlds generall <hi>Aſsiſes,</hi> which will beginne and end in one day <hi>(for the Lord will make a ſhort count in the Earth)</hi> the <hi>Iudge</hi> of this vniuerſall Circuite, is the Iudge of all Iudges, the Lord chiefe Iuſtice, the Sonne of God, but viſible in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as the Sonne of man (<hi>Luk.</hi> 21.27) clothed as in <hi>ſcarlet robes,</hi> with the power and maieſty of his Father, (<hi>Matth.</hi> 16.27.) his <hi>Bench</hi> a tribunall or throne of State, (<hi>Rom.</hi> 14.10.) the <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of the Bench his <hi>Aſſeſſours,</hi> the twelue Peeres of Chriſtendome, his twelue <hi>Apoſtles, (Matth.</hi> 19.28.) his <hi>Crier,</hi> an Archangell with the ſound of a ſhrill Trumpe, that ſhall eccho ouer all the world, and waken the bodies, that are dead and rotten, (1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.16.) the <hi>Priſoners,</hi> all mankind (2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10.) our <hi>Cauſe,</hi> to anſwere vpon Life and Death. The Diuell comes forth for the <hi>Accuſer,</hi> that would alſo faine be the <hi>Executioner;</hi> the Conſcience is produced for an vntainted <hi>Witneſſe,</hi> and the <hi>allegations</hi> are proued by pregnant Records, (<hi>Reu.</hi> 20.12.) <hi>The Bookes are ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and the dead are iudged of thoſe things, which are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Bookes, according to their workes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two Bookes are to be opened,
<note place="margin">The euidence moſt euident.</note> 
               <hi>Libriſcientiae Dei, &amp; conſcientiaenoſtrae;</hi> the <hi>Lieger</hi> Booke of Gods knowledge, and the <hi>Count</hi> Book of our own conſcience, which ſhall then be inlarged by a new Edition. For in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and former Edition of our conſciences Booke, ſome things wee <hi>cannot</hi> reade, ſome wee doe not reade, ſome wee will not reade, and ſome wee will not ſuffer others to read.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Here many things are but dimmely, and as it were but <hi>halfe printed</hi> in our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ſo that our dull eyes <hi>cannot</hi> read them (whence <hi>Dauid, Pſa.</hi> 19.12. <hi>Who knoweth how oft he offendeth? Oh
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:25202:17"/>cleanſe thou mee from my ſecret ſins:)</hi> but then the print will be clearer, our ſecret ſinnes legible, and the ſcales of mortal ignorance being fallen off, <hi>We ſhal know our ſelues, euen as we are known of God, who is greater then our hart,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> &amp; knoweth all things,</hi> 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.20. In this Edition are many things of a ſmall print, which becauſe we wil not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble our ſelues to put on the ſpectacles of <hi>Care</hi> and <hi>conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration,</hi> we paſſe ouer and doe not read them: but then they ſhall be ſet out in a <hi>larger</hi> print, and the ſins, that now ſeeme too <hi>ſmal</hi> to be regarded,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> wil then be ſeen too great to be indured. Here many things being diſtaſtfull, we blot out of our Booke, and will not read them: but then they ſhall reuiue, and will wee, nill wee,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> wee ſhall remember them. Here we finde in ſome paſſages, ſuch inky and vgly characters of ſinnes, that wee are <hi>loth any other</hi> ſhould read with vs, and therefore wee ſhew them onely a faire <hi>outſide</hi> gilded with <hi>hypocriticall</hi> ſhew. But then the <hi>Booke ſhall be laid open,</hi> and lying open, the faire couering ſhall lye couered; and all that wee haue done, ſpoken, yea or thought, ſhall be obuious to euery eye, and as looking-<hi>glaſſes</hi> ſet in a round, doe each re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent to other their ſeuerall obiects, ſo that euery one in particular, containeth all the ſhewes they haue in generall: So in the Iudgement day, our conſcience which now is our priuate, ſhall then bee a common <hi>glaſſe;</hi> each ſhall ſee in other, and euery one ſhall ſee in all, whatſoeuer lieth now conceiled in the ſecret bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, <hi>There is nothing hid, that ſhall not bee reueiled.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.26. The effects hereof. 1. With the godly.</note>
            </p>
            <p>O, what exultation will then crowne the heads of ſuch, as can ſay with faithfull <hi>Paul, Act.</hi> 23.1. <hi>I haue in all good conſcience ſerued God vntill this day!</hi> when they ſhall ſee their good deeds, whereof ſome themſelues
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:25202:18"/>concealed from vaine-glorious applauſe. Some were <hi>drowned</hi> by wayward vnthankfulnes, and ſome <hi>miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrued</hi> by ſiniſter conceits, to ſee them all <hi>notified</hi> in their freſh and liuely colours. And oh, what <hi>confuſion</hi> will couer the face of thoſe fooliſh wizards,
<note place="margin">2. With the wicked.</note> that care more to <hi>cloake,</hi> then to <hi>cure</hi> their vlcers! when they ſhall ſee that wickedneſſe, which they now <hi>hide</hi> curiouſly, from their neereſt kinſman, and deareſt friend (but can neuer be hid from the <hi>all-ſeeing God,</hi> and his <hi>intelligencer,</hi> their inward conſcience) to be <hi>expoſed</hi> in that day to the full ſight of <hi>Angels,</hi> and <hi>men,</hi> and <hi>diuels,</hi> and all.</p>
            <p>The euidence being thus giuen in,
<note place="margin">The ſentence.</note> and the <hi>deedes</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing apparent, both <hi>that</hi> they are, and <hi>what</hi> they are, their <hi>number</hi> and <hi>weight</hi> is taken: and as <hi>they that haue done good, ſhall</hi> all <hi>goe into euerlaſting life,</hi> ſo of them, they that haue done <hi>beſt,</hi> ſhall ſit <hi>higheſt</hi> in glory; not one of their good workes, (no, not a <hi>cuppe of cold water (Mat.</hi> 10.42.) ſhall ſlippe vnrewarded. And as <hi>they that haue done euill,</hi> ſhall be caſt into <hi>euerlaſting fire,</hi> ſo they that haue done worſt, ſhall be plunged into <hi>deepeſt</hi> torments, not one of their villanies but ſhall haue his ſcourge.</p>
            <p>And ſhall I need to adde the concluſion?
<note place="margin">This ſhould breed a wary feare.</note> doth not the vſe make inference of it ſelf, therfore <hi>paſſe the time of your dwelling herein feare?</hi> Can we ſtand by this glowing, this flaming, this ſcorching, this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſuming fire of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and not be warmed? not heat? not ſweat? yea, and not frie with <hi>feare?</hi> are wee not more like <hi>Salamanders</hi> then men, if we can liue vntouched in ſo furious a fire? What?
<note place="margin">Generally at all times.</note> doth God our Iudge ſee all our workes? and ſhall we not feare to ſinne, while he looketh full vpon vs? ſhall euery action be diſplaied in the view of all the world? and ſhall wee yet offend boldly, in hope of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecy?
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:25202:18"/>will euery offence call for his ſeuerall plague? and ſhall we not feare to <hi>heape vp wrath againſt the day of wrath?</hi> Yea this, me thinks, ſhould be a bridle in the noſtrils of the moſt deſperate Caitife; that although he care not to doe good, as hauing no hope of reward in heauen, yet hee ſhould feare to multiply offences, leſt thereby hee multiply his torments, and make his hell more helliſh to himſelfe.</p>
            <p>A matter that would craue to bee amplified, if the time craued not the contrary. For in this aduenterous age of ours, wherin ſo many are like flies, that ceaſe not to play about the candle, til they burne in the flame, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more to be feared, then that we feare too little. They are indeed the <hi>better</hi> ſort, which are <hi>directed</hi> by <hi>loue,</hi> but they are the <hi>greater</hi> ſort, who are <hi>corrected</hi> by <hi>feare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> writeth, that the <hi>Almond</hi> tree being growne old and barren, muſt haue <hi>nailes</hi> driuen into the roote, whereby the ſuperfluous gummy humour being let out, it becommeth fruitfull anew. How happy ſhould I thinke my labour, if I could driue this naile of <hi>feare</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the roote of your hearts; not only you ancients, who haue <hi>the Almond tree flouriſhing</hi> in your heads (<hi>Eccleſiaſ.</hi> 12.5.) but you youngers alſo, that haue need of prick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>phlebotomy,</hi> to euacuate that luxuriant, and ſupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant humour of preſumptuous boldneſſe? that ſo becomming <hi>fruitfull in all good workes,</hi> the pricking of this naile of feare, may preuent the <hi>felling</hi> of that <hi>axe</hi> of <hi>furie,</hi> which is <hi>laid to the roote of the tree,</hi> whereby <hi>euery tree which bringeth not forth good fruit, is to be hewne downe, and caſt</hi> into endleſſe <hi>fire, Matth.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>The time thus preſſing me, I cannot ſtand to preſſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:25202:19"/>this vnto the preſent occaſion:
<note place="margin">Specially in the preſent buſineſſe.</note> onely I muſt deſire, as all in generall, ſo in ſpeciall you that act any part in this weekes ſolemne buſines, that the Law may be vſed lawfully, not for the wronging of right, but the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of wrong; that in all your pleadings, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer other proceeding, your retaine <hi>God</hi> for your <hi>Counſeller,</hi> and his <hi>feare</hi> for your <hi>Sollicitour.</hi> Let the view of theſe <hi>Aſsiſes</hi> whiſper to your conſcience a <hi>Memorandum</hi> of thoſe <hi>vniuerſall</hi> Aſſiſes: remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in all your proiects and courſes, that the <hi>Lord Iudge,</hi> and your <hi>Conſcience</hi> the <hi>Witneſſe,</hi> doe now ſtand watching what you doe, and will then diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all, when you ſhall ſtand to your triall for life or death. Doe but remember this, and apply it cloſe to your heart, with good <hi>Iehoſaphats</hi> Caueat, 2. <hi>Chronicles,</hi> 19.7. <hi>Wherefore now, let the feare of the Lord bee vpon you, take heede, and doe it.</hi> This is little enough, and yet this little may bee enough; <hi>Let the feare of the Lord bee vpon you, take heede, and looke to it.</hi> Let mee giue but one ſtroke more, to driue this <hi>naile</hi> to the head with the <hi>hammer</hi> of Gods Word, euen that <hi>aphoriſme</hi> of <hi>Salomon, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbs</hi> 28.14, <hi>Bleſſed is the man that feareth alway; but hee that hardeneth his heart, ſhall fall into euill.</hi> And now come wee briefely to ſumme vp all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Wee haue ſeene the two feete,
<note place="margin">Both feares vnited.</note> whereon God walketh before vs, and the two feete, on which wee muſt both follow him, and walke before him. His two feete are the mercy of a <hi>Father,</hi> and the iuſtice of a <hi>Iudge:</hi> our two feete are the feare of his mercies, and the <hi>feare</hi> of his iudgements. If the body of our <hi>feare</hi> bee
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:25202:19"/>not ſupported with both theſe legges, it cannot goe vpright, but will fall lame, <hi>aut nimium ſperando, aut deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perando.</hi> If our thoughts ſhould hop all vpon his <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi> without his iudgements, wee ſhould fall vpon the right ſide in a <hi>preſuming confidence;</hi> if all vpon his <hi>iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> without his mercie, wee ſhould tumble vpon the left ſide in <hi>deſpairing diffidence:</hi> both theſe ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters will make our walking ſteddy and vpright. If thou finde thy ſelfe <hi>drowzie</hi> in goodneſſe, ſteppe foorth with the <hi>right</hi> legge, the <hi>feare</hi> of his <hi>mercies:</hi> a good <hi>motiue</hi> to vertue: if <hi>tempted</hi> to ſinne, ſteppe backe with the left legge, the <hi>feare</hi> of his <hi>iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:</hi> a good <hi>retentiue</hi> from vice. God is a gracious <hi>Father:</hi> harken to this, O thou that haſt ſinned, and art <hi>repenting.</hi> And God is a ſeuere <hi>Iudge;</hi> har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to this, O thou, that haſt repented, and art vpon <hi>ſinning.</hi> Let the meditation of God as a <hi>Father,</hi> be as the bleſſed <hi>Angels,</hi> that carried <hi>Lot</hi> out of ſinfull <hi>Sodome;</hi> but <hi>timor addidit alas;</hi> if the ſoule will be lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, and caſt an eye backe againe, let the apprehenſion of his <hi>iudgement,</hi> be as the ſight of <hi>fire and brimſtone</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind vs, to put wings vnto our feete. Let both together <hi>breede</hi> and <hi>keepe</hi> in vs a care and conſcience of all our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, that hee which is fallen, make haſte to riſe, and <hi>hee that ſtandeth, take heed leſt hee fall:</hi> and that all of vs in <hi>awfull,</hi> and yet <hi>chearefull</hi> obedience, <hi>worke out our ſaluation with feare and trembling, Philippians</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>Then as that <hi>concordia diſcors,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Produce hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py effects.</note> or rather <hi>diſcordia concors,</hi> in <hi>Dauids</hi> ditty (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.1. <hi>I will ſing mercy and iudgement</hi>) the diſcordant notes of <hi>mercy</hi> and <hi>iudgement,</hi> doe make a bleſſed ſymphony in Gods proceedings
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:25202:20"/>vpon earth; ſo his Spouſe in ſinging her Loue-ſong of <hi>mercy,</hi> and reliſhing her notes with the <hi>quauering</hi> of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious <hi>feare,</hi> will make acceptable, and harmonicall mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke in the eares of heauen. Finally, if we thus paſſe the time <hi>of our dwelling here</hi> in this louing <hi>feare,</hi> wee ſhall paſſe from it in his louing fauour, and <hi>dwell</hi> with him for <hi>time,</hi> that ſhall neuer <hi>paſſe</hi> in loue without <hi>feare.</hi> To the which dwelling, O thou that <hi>dwelleſt in the Heauens,</hi> bring vs, &amp;c.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSALM. 86.11.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Teach me thy way, O Lord, that I may walke in thy truth: vnite my heart to feare thy name.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:25202:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
